everyone knows that ice is colder than
water but usually you're not going to
freeze water just by adding some ice
cubes today we're going to see if we can
super cool our ice to the point where
actually freeze water solid
[Music]
today we're doing a fun experiment using
liquid nitrogen ice and water three
different levels of temperature here and
we're gonna see if we can take some
regular cubed ice put it in liquid
nitrogen until it's absurdly cold and
then drop it into water we're trying to
see if we can make the water hit sort of
a flashpoint but in Reverse where it
will just suddenly freeze because we've
dropped the temperature so much normally
if you put ice in the water you're just
gonna get cold water we want to see if
we can make the ice so much colder than
water that the water will actually
freeze in the process of trying to warm
the ice out here's the basic idea we've
got some liquid nitrogen we've got a
bunch of ice cubes in some water we're
gonna dip that ice into liquid nitrogen
cooling it down way more than a normal
freezer would and then we'll see if that
supercooled ice can steal enough heat
out of water for it to freeze we have a
number of stemware cups and I'm using
this type because I think it might have
less glass in contact with the water
heating it back up a lot of the time a
glass cup will have a sort of thick
bottom to it and that seems like it
would just hold enough heat that it
would just keep our water from freezing
so I'm hoping that the stemware will
have a little bit less of that we'll see
if it works to start off as a sort of
control test we're going to pour some
water into a cup measure the temperature
and then add a bunch of ice and see what
temperature it drops it down to guys
quick announcement we've got some shirts
that are going on sale in our store now
that's right guys for the next two weeks
the I tried it at home in the look mom
no hands shirts are only $19.99 they're
really soft so if you want one click the
link in the description below this water
is chilled I've had it in the fridge for
a while but I don't think it's anywhere
near freezing nine point two eight point
nine degrees Celsius let's add some ice
into our cup see what change we get
get some nice condensation on the
outside of the glass always a good sign
things are cooling down it's only been a
minute or so but let's see what
temperature were clocking in at we're
already several degrees cooler than
where we were before 37 degrees
Fahrenheit dropping still a little bit
let's give that another minute of
stirring and see where we get
[Music]
down to 34 Fahrenheit or 1.1 Celsius so
that's pretty cold that's getting very
close to the temperature of the phase
shift between liquid and solid water hmm
chilly now that was fairly cold at least
in terms of food weed and temperatures
we regularly experience but over here
we've got liquid nitrogen which of
course is a whole different beast and
doesn't really even register to us son
just how cold it is for instance I'm not
going to put the thermometer in the
liquid nitrogen that's far too cold I'm
just gonna put it in the vapors between
the surface of the liquid and the top of
the container and we're below zero
Fahrenheit by a lot and we're
approaching some of the coldest
temperatures ever experienced by anyone
on earth and at that point we have
gotten so cold that our thermometer can
no longer handle it somewhere around 60
degrees below zero Fahrenheit it's too
cold and like I said this is not in the
liquid nitrogen liquid nitrogen is still
down there below a little bit so now we
are going to take some ice and we're
gonna supercooled it in our liquid
nitrogen and then see what happens when
we introduce it to our water alright
we've stopped bubbling which means we
probably have our ice cube down to the
temperature we're very close to the
temperature of the liquid nitrogen
itself just gonna set this on a counter
try and put our temperature probe in
contact with it zero Fahrenheit that's
negative eighteen Celsius all right
we're at about 50 degrees below
Fahrenheit and about 45 degrees below
Celsius I think it's actually far colder
than that but because the probe is just
resting on it it's still getting
exposure to the air around us it's not
gonna drop all the way down to the
temperature of the ice but now let's see
what happens if we take some water and
several supercooled ice cubes and see
what we can do to the temperature of the
water that's about where our water is 48
degrees Fahrenheit layer of ice just
forms around the tongs so fast because
they're almost as cold as liquid
nitrogen themselves
our single supercooled ice cube has only
reduced the temperature of our cup of
water by about three degrees but let's
try adding several of them we had a
handful before when you tried normal ice
and here you see we can get a handful of
supercooled ice cubes
[Music]
liquid nitrogen is just boiling away our
ice is so hot it's causing our liquid
nitrogen to boil
looks like we have frozen our ice cubes
water is starting off at about 45 and a
half Fahrenheit our super cold ice cubes
they hit the water and the water just
forms a frozen barrier around them
almost immediately and that happened
enough that all of our ice cubes have
now stuck together got the temperature
down to 35 and a half degrees Fahrenheit
I think what we're seeing now I was
hoping that we could sort of cool the
water down to where it was almost at a
point with just a another little bit of
cold supercooled ice would drop in and I
would sort of caused the whole cup to
freeze mostly what we're having happen
is as I drop a piece of supercooled ice
in it forms a layer of ice around itself
so just the water that's directly in
contact with it loses enough heat to
turn into ice and then it doesn't spread
to the rest of the cup it kind of just
slowly grows like as this chunk of ice
has been sitting in the cup it's just
been getting like a thicker and thicker
layer forming over it
and it's just begun to form a layer
around itself it's kind of like a pearl
forming in an oyster it just builds up
more and more around it I'm gonna leave
this in here and keep stirring it and
hope that it keeps stealing heat away
from the water cooling it down even more
but I've also got some new ice cubes
into liquid nitrogen and I'm gonna take
this sort of blob cube out and put those
new ones in and see if we can sort of
keep going because it is lowering the
temperature in the cup but I'm kind of
wondering if we keep doing this
several times if we keep adding more
even colder ice will we get to a point
where the whole cup is just like too
cold and just all solidifies to really
push this to a limit we've taken our cup
filled it up with our supercooled ice
and then poured some cold water on top
and even with that while we have a lot
of ice forming around our cubes I don't
think we've managed to freeze the whole
cup we had an experiment to see if we
could get a cup of water to flash freeze
when we put our supercooled ice cubes
into the water it just starts forming an
ice barrier around the cube and it
really doesn't do a good job of cooling
down all of the water together I've sort
of moved to seeing if I can do a
different experiment because I was so
fascinated by how those layers of ice
formed I'm gonna see if I can take our
cube of ice and make sort of a rainbow
shell around it I've got six different
colors of water and I'm gonna try doing
each color and then like a gap layer of
regular ice and see how well this is
gonna work
[Music]
all right here is my magic egg of ice I
don't really know how to break through
this nice and cleanly so I'm just gonna
kind of cut down and hope I get
something of a clean edge a little bit
of a clean edge not great freezing so
much it has sort of shattered into
pieces but that is really cool rainbow
look right there that seriously looks
like the inside of a jawbreaker
alright this turned out really cool and
you can see really clearly how thick
each layer was like you can count how
many times I dipped it into each color
where I just dipped into the water to
sort of separate it but overall this is
really neat and so unfortunately we
couldn't get whole cups of ice to freeze
solid but this ice layering thing worked
out really nicely and it took a ton of
food coloring to get it to really pick
up the color but the rainbow ice looks
gorgeous try and get it like dip it in
water
[Music]
layered ice experiment worked even
better than I hoped it would this turned
into quite the jawbreaker looking piece
it's fascinating like you can just
clearly see all the layers I think we
got some good shots where you can see
the differentiation even now you can see
a little bit as it separates from one
into the next some people can taste food
coloring I'm not sure if I'm one of
those people it just tastes like ice to
me so whether or not you can get water
to reach sort of a flashpoint by putting
supercooled ice cubes into it I'm not
sure maybe you can but none of our
experiments got that to work we tried
pouring really cold water over our
supercooled ice we tried putting
supercooled ice cubes into the water
over and over and we just never got the
water to cool down more and I'm pretty
sure it's because any water that comes
in contact with the supercooled ice just
starts forming a layer of ice around it
we've done experiments on the channel
before where we showed you how you can
put a water bottle in the freezer for a
certain amount of time then just by
hitting the bottle or tipping it out you
can get all of it to freeze at once but
that's not what we're going for here and
I'm sure if we had one of those and
dropped a supercooled ice cube in it
would freeze but at that point anything
makes it freeze we're seeing if we could
use our supercooled ice to get the water
down to that temperature and that wasn't
very successful but I'm gonna focus on
the fact that it was really successful
making our little rainbow ice cube ball
things here and they were a lot of fun
you got great variants of color guys
that's all for today but the fun does
not end here that box at the top will
take you directly to our most recent
video you should go check that out the
other box will show you what YouTube
thinks you should be watching next if
you are not a subscriber hit this bottom
to get in the club and that way you'll
never miss out on a video don't forget
to ring that Bell and we will see you in
the next one talk to you then